Thank you so much for joining us.
We have a ton to do today, and that's super exciting.
There we go.
So thank you, Rachel.
If you're just joining us from First Sound, we spent the last several weeks covering the
seven I Am statements of Jesus, as well as the seven miraculous signs found in the Gospel
of John.
The same thing we got for God is this dual role of Jesus, by seeing this humanity, how
his light is in every way, and he's the bondage and how he's the total revelation of an invisible
God, how he's clearly like no other.
This place here, John writes as the disciple of Jesus, is about this person who he is walking
with, who is fully God and fully human.
Now, I search for, like, those cool analogies to build up, but, like, as I'm doing my study
and stuff, the Gospel of John is like an onion.
And hopefully you guys are not evil.
As articulated famously by an ogre, what?
Can we get it?
Ogres love layers.
Onions have layers.
The Gospel of John also has layers.
So today, we're going to try to peel back and look at some of those layers today.
Last week, if you remember, where I started unpacking what is referred to as the upper room
discourse in John 14.
This was Jesus' invitation to join him in this new creation with the declaration,
I am the way, the truth, and the life.
Remember the analogy Ron used about the door?
Yeah?
So Jesus is inviting us into something, something bigger than ourselves, and I believe Jesus is
inviting us into this new creation that he's ushering in.
These are the last two of the I am in statements from Jesus.
I am the way, the truth, and the life, and I am the Bible.
Jesus is using this last time, just like a place would, to prepare his disciples for
the events that will change human history, if we know it.
His death, his burial, his resurrection, and in his future ascension.
Thank you.
Please get this.
This is Jesus, God incarnate made flesh, giving his closest followers the last instruction
before the whole world gets turned upside down.
Church, do we try this real quick before we get started?
Dear Heavenly Father, we come before you today thanking you for your word.
Thanking you for the guidance that you've given us.
Thank you for this book that we call the Bible.
Thank you for your inner word, the Holy Spirit that takes this out of the word of Jesus and
convicts us and drives us to be more faithful followers than you.
Thank you for bringing the cup of suffering on the cross, for your victorious resurrection and your ascension to the throne of heaven.
Thank you for being more than the king we want.
Thank you for being the king that we need.
Give you to the soft hearts to take away what you would have us take away from today's lesson.
And may it be something that abides in us as we learn to better abide in you.
We pray all this for your glory and our neighbor's good and in the holy and powerful name of Jesus we pray.
Amen.
So, today, let's go ahead and start unpacking some of our Scripture today.
We're going to be turning to John 15, if you have your Bibles.
It's on your app.
I'll be in this ESV today.
We're going to be reading verses 1 through 17.
I am the three vine and my father is the gardener.
Every branch in me that does not produce fruit, he remains.
And he cleans every branch that produces fruit so that it will produce more fruit.
You are already clean because of the word I have spoken to you.
Remain in me and I in you.
Just as a branch is unable to produce fruit by itself unless it remains in the vine,
neither can you unless you remain in me.
I am the vine.
You are the branchers.
The one who remain in me and I in him produces my fruit.
Because you can be nothing without me.
If anyone does not remain in me, he is thrown aside like a branch of new rivers.
They gather them, throw them into the fire, and they are burned.
If you remain in me and my words remain in you, ask whatever you want and it will be done for you.
My father is glorified by this, that you produce much fruit and prove to be my disciple.
First, when I am just, as the father has loved me, I have also loved you.
Jesus reiterates his thanks, remain in my love.
As you see my commands, you will remain in my love just as I have kept my father's commands and remain in his love.
I told you these things so that my joy may be in you and your joy may be made complete.
This is my commandment, love one another as I have loved you.
No one has greater love than this, to lay down his life for his friends.
You are my friends, if you do what I command you.
I do not call you servants anymore because a servant doesn't know what his master is doing.
I have called you friends because I have known to you everything I have heard from my father.
You do not choose me, but I have changed you.
I have appointed you to go and produce fruit, which is fruit to your name.
Whatever you ask, the father in my name, he will give you.
This is what I command you.
Love one another.
So I can spend the rest of our time, compassion, verse 17, and how we as the church fall short and command of Jesus.
Right?
Am I the only one that doesn't love my neighbors well all the time?
But I'm going to let you and the Holy Spirit work on that with your host and self.
What I want to cover today is the three images found in this section of Christmas.
The image of the vine, the branches, and the gardener.
We're going to start with this image of the vine.
Like we covered before, the I am statement of Jesus is this throwback to Moses encountering Yahweh in the burning blood of Exodus 3.
If you look there in verse 14, God replies to Moses,
I am who I am.
This phrase in Hebrew would have both a past tense and a future tense,
which echoes Jesus' statement, Proclamation of Revelation,
I am the Alpha, the Omega, the Beginning, and the End.
This I am statement titles Yahweh as someone outside of his creation.
Someone who is self-sustaining and someone who's ascended.
A being outside of time and space as we know it.
But here is Jesus.
Who is all these things, but is chosen to enter his creation as one of us.
It's John 1, right?
The word between flesh.
And I'll add those Colossians 1 again.
Jesus, this being of the invisible God.
So when you see Jesus, you can see Yahweh.
This is the last of the seven I am statements.
So far we've talked about, I'm the bread of life.
I'm the light of the world.
I'm the boar.
I'm the good shepherd.
I'm the resurrection and the life.
I'm the way, the truth, and the life.
Now, last one, I am the true God.
Jesus is echoing the sentiment of, I am who I am.
This is the last of the series, so I want to make sure you guys are talking with me.
We all talking?
Jesus is making this statement?
Jesus in this lesson is the true God and the Father is the God.
I'm going to give you my best to unpack context here because I think it gets lost in our Western cultural lenses.
With current events going on, I am just going on.
With current events going on, especially with the nation-state of Israel, I want to give some upfront information.
I'm going to be talking a lot about Israel today, especially from an Old Testament, first-century concept.
I'm not referencing the current nation-state of Israel.
I'm referencing biblical Israel.
Cool?
You got it?
Throughout the Old Testament, there are references to Israel as the body.
They see themselves, this biblical nation of Israel, see themselves as the great body of the ones who have God, Yahweh.
From our note-takers, we've got references.
Jeremiah 2.21, I have planted you like a choice vine in sound and reliable stock.
How then did you turn against me into this corrupt, wild vine?
Psalm 82, verses 8 and 16, you're transplanting the vine from Egypt, you drove out the mansions and planted it.
Verse 16, you're vine that's cut down and burned with fire, as you'll reduce your people's page.
Isaiah 10, 1 through 2, Israel was a spreading vine.
He brought forth fruit for himself.
As his fruit incense, he built more altars.
As his land prospered, he adorned his sacred stones.
Their heart is deceitful.
And now, they must bear their guilt.
The Lord will demolish their altars and destroy their sacred stones.
And then, last but not least, Ezekiel 15, which is kind of the catalyst in comparative Scripture to John 15.
If you turn in your Bibles, the title of the chapter will be something like,
A portable, the useless vine, or Jerusalem, a useless vine, or Jerusalem, a fruitless vine.
Are we seeing this kind of trend?
I'm going to read Ezekiel 15, verses 6 through 8.
Therefore, this is what the Lord God says.
Like the wood of the bond among the trees of the forest, which I have given to the fire and the fuel,
I will give up the residents of Jerusalem.
I will turn against them, though they may escape from the fires, but it will consume them.
And you will know that I am the Lord when I turn against them.
For he's saying, I will make the land desolate because they have acted unfaithfully.
This is the declaration of the Lord God.
See, these pictures of the bond were well imprinted in the minds of the Jews.
According to ancient historians, there was even a carving of a grapevine engraved on the temple entrance.
I guess you would.
At the time of Jesus, the golden grapevine was draped across the four columns at the entrance of the temple.
Procebus records that its beauty was such that it was known as a marvel of size and artistry
to all who saw what costliness of the material had been constructed.
The Mishnah, if you're familiar, says the people would sometimes make a free will offering
by purchasing a golden leaf, dairy, or cluster, which the priests would attach to this golden gospel.
He often goes to give generously to the temple as they lose and start on golden leaves.
This was a custom that most were familiar with, if not all were familiar with, in Jerusalem.
This was the identity for the nation of Israel.
Good, bad, or indifferent, they saw themselves as the grapevine of Yahweh.
Even though through rebellion, corruption, disobedience, and unfaithfulness,
they were this poison grapevine.
This was their connection to God.
This was their identity.
No one else's.
Trevon?
No.
Jesus kind of turns out in your, it's not for John 15, right?
That I am the true body.
The people who are listening, these disciples, the reader of the Gospels,
Israel is the son, they're the son of Abraham.
You might think you're the body.
You might think you're the body, but I am the true body.
See, when Jesus depicts himself as the true body,
he's undoubtedly contrasting himself with this artificial body,
this identity body of the nation of Israel.
Jesus is offering himself as a solution to their unfaithfulness.
And here's the next slide.
A little rule of contrast here.
If Jesus was the three body, John 15,
and Israel's a useless body, Ezekiel 15,
see, I'm not trying to be unnecessarily hurt here,
but I want to unpack this through it.
Jesus is always the focal point.
Jesus is always the true body.
So this idea of Jesus being the body sucks all the air out of the self-righteousness of Israel,
and it should suck out all of our self-righteousness.
Jesus is coaching those disciples on where their allegiance needs to be.
It's about to get harder.
It's going to get real harder.
Jesus is the body because he was faithful when Israel was not.
Jesus is the true body because he was obedient even unto death when Israel was not.
How are we as a people, as individuals,
particularly I like to use community language,
as a community, as we're not connected to the true body?
We're not.
We're useless, right?
John 15.
We're just dead branches.
So if you were God's chosen people,
the friend of Abraham,
a people,
bring in the feeling that God would show himself to the world.
Deuteronomy 14.2 says,
You have been set apart.
This is the nation of Israel.
You have been set apart as fully to the Lord your God.
And he has chosen you from all the nations of the earth
to be his own special pleasure.
See, Israel had this mindset,
but they were the bond.
They were the chosen people,
and they would be the conduit
through whom God would bring them aside
to save them from the world.
Get this.
Get this point.
They would be the conduit
through whom God would save them from the world.
Rather, God, so in his faithfulness,
his creation would save the world,
the whole world through Israel
in the form of Jesus, the Messiah,
the Savior of the world.
So we're just saying that this morning, right?
For God so loved all of what?
World that he gave us
is one of the begotten Son.
God's prayer has always been from Genesis
to redeem his whole creation,
something he calls very good.
So it's only challenging with this today.
Do we have an identity mindset,
an Israel identity mindset?
Have we become a useless bond?
Are you connected to the true bond
where we start to rely on religious systems,
moral purpose,
our own self-righteousness,
the secret for these?
Do we view ourselves
as the chosen people
that God needs to save from this world?
Or are we a people
connected to a Savior
that plans on saving the world from love?
Before we move on to the next idea,
Jesus is the true body.
He should be our identity.
Now to the branches.
And hopefully I've made
like an optimistic sandwich
out of this.
Like, that's God's end.
We're like the messy roast beef
in the middle.
And like,
God's the other end of the sandwich.
Like,
that's my goal.
Verse 2,
every branch in me
that does not produce fruit,
he removes...
Someone's going to be mad for a second.
Hold on.
Every branch in me
that does not produce fruit,
he removes.
And he claims every branch
to produce his fruit,
so that it will produce
more fruit.
Every branch in me
that does not produce fruit,
he removes.
He removes.
Come on,
you guys realize,
like the band dresser,
right?
The gardener in this title.
This verse is...
Steve, I'm a lion's ear.
But this verse
and others in this section
used to make me cringe.
Right?
And we thought of that
where it's like,
oh God,
I want to be free.
I don't necessarily want this
to have the new
they improve
in order to keep it.
I think we're going to...
I think some of that
is true in this section,
but I think we're going to
dive a little bit deeper today
as I thought of you guys
and really get to the heart
of that fruit.
I want to...
I'm going to stick
on this part a little bit.
Ryan made this point last week
and I thought it was a good one.
I think...
I think the church
often weaponizes
some of these verses
to scare people.
And I'm not saying
the pastor doesn't have
some scary portions with it.
I think it's valuable.
Like if I just dropped
this verse to you,
I'm going to think it's value, right?
God is going to bring you.
But I want you to think
in touch for me.
This is...
None of my heart
and passion
behind my disciples thing.
I want you to think
in touch for me.
What's going on here?
Right?
We just had the upper room
in John 14, right?
Not...
Not yet.
So we just had the upper room
in John 14.
The end of John 14,
Jesus said,
let's go.
Where are they going?
You guys know this
from the internet.
I heard it.
Garden.
Garden of Gethsemane.
Spoiler alert,
Jesus is arrested
by the religious council there
if you're not that far ahead.
But like you...
This is Jesus
walking through the garden
on his way
to be arrested.
Like...
This is the last
coaching session.
This is not...
Judgment is a real thing.
This is a coaching session.
This is God's...
Get this.
Please.
Jesus is inviting us
into something.
And you can see
right ahead
of John 16,
you'll see this verse
beginning along.
One eye is
holding these things
to keep you from
stumbling.
The first two.
It brings every branch
to produce his fruit
so they will produce
more fruit.
So,
I guess,
go back to Jesus.
What is
as Jesus
giving...
What is the verse
saying to us?
What is his fruit?
Could it be,
because we're good
amazing Christians,
could it just be
the fruit of the Spirit?
Glory to God.
That's a question.
Yes,
it could be,
no,
it could be...
Yes,
it could be,
sure.
I agree with those
of you that said it.
Sure,
it could be
Paul expounding
on Jesus' ideas
of fruit
in God's response.
I'm cool with that.
But again,
contextually,
let's see where
this John 15 thread
takes us.
Jesus goes on
to say in verses
4-5,
remain in me
and I
and you
just as a branch
is unable
to produce fruit
by itself
unless it remains
in the vine
neither to you
unless you remain
in me.
Versus,
I am the vine,
you are the branch
of the one
who remains in me
and I in him
produces much fruit
because you can
do nothing
without me.
Now,
during my studies
and stuff,
I read some commentators
and like,
the context is,
it's,
well not some days,
it's some of the
songs I listen to too,
where there's this idea
of like,
you can do nothing
without me
and they're like,
we're four,
you can do stuff.
And these are like,
I get,
I don't feel like
Jews is usually
a euphemism here,
like,
and then I did
end up finding
a commentator
that I was like,
man,
I untapped it
really well
and this idea
of abiding in me
and you can do
nothing without me.
This idea of
remaining in Jesus,
in other words
that other translations
use to see us,
maybe he doesn't use it,
but this word abide,
are we familiar
with that language
abide in me
and I
and you.
It's an infinite word.
I think we can,
that's typically
also what I'm guilty of this,
right,
we can power,
I'm going to say,
I'm still going to say this,
I get really excited
with you for life.
I read my Bible
in a year.
It's fantastic.
It's great.
And this one,
after you read your Bible
in a year,
don't stop.
Go back and slow down.
Like,
let's read this thing.
I think we can power through
and I'm guilty of this.
How many times
I've read John 15
about me and I am you?
Great.
That's it.
Come on, Jesus.
Let's go.
And I think there's more truth.
This is an intimate word.
It's where we get the word
abide phrase,
which means
a place where one lives,
a home,
a dwelling place.
There's a,
you feel the intimacy to that.
Dustin White,
a fellow brother and pastor,
puts it like this in his book,
A Real Father's Prayer.
And you hit a couple slides
that hit if you got from mine.
Remaining is a speechless
nearness.
Remaining in Jesus
is an abiding attention
to the connection
we share with need.
Remaining in Jesus
demands a shift
in our perspective
of how we normally
feel inclined to relate to him.
That's it with anybody
or just me.
Like,
I normally do not feel inclined
to relate to Jesus
by just being with him.
Right?
Typically,
and I'm counting
many Christians,
we use the language
of doing things for God.
And understandably so.
However,
having a faith
in which the primary mode
by which we can relate
to God
is doing things for him
does not mean
that we even
have to commune with him.
All during the end,
getting squared away
on our arbitrary
religious checklist,
right?
Things to do.
See,
that's in poor
and poor language.
That's in God's language.
See,
God calls us
to abide
in him
and he with us.
See,
this intimacy
abiding in God
and remaining in him
denotes a love
and a life
shared with God.
Not for God,
And this is where
I found a ton
of value in this
and I hope for you
do too.
This is temple language.
And I know that may be
foreign to some of us,
but the first century Jews,
they would have recognized it
in all the details
that came with that language.
Remain in me
and I in you.
Writing last week,
if you guys remember,
it is kind of a
cliff notes version
of the Old Testament,
the temple,
the tabernacle.
Yep.
So the presence,
I'm going to do that again.
The presence of God
led the nation of Israel
out of Egypt,
right,
out of bondage
through the wilderness
by being a pillar
of fire by night,
a pillar of cloud by day.
Remember that?
So what,
and then when we build
the tabernacle,
right,
God gives specific instructions
on building this ark
of the covenant,
the ark of the covenant,
like we talked about
last week's house,
is what?
It has the mercy seat
on top.
What else?
Ten Commandments?
Revelation,
all the things.
But yes,
the manna
and the,
not zero,
and staff.
So I said,
the law,
right,
that's the important part,
the law sets there.
Between the law
and God,
we have what?
Mercy seat,
right,
so the mercy seat
is God's throne
that gets sprinkled
with blood,
right,
in the atonement,
the day of atonement.
The presence of God
sat on the mercy seat
in the tabernacle.
The presence of God
sat on the mercy seat
in Solomon's temple
when that's filled.
This was a
house of God
and a home,
a glowing place
and a bow,
right?
The idea of the
full of holiness
is this is God's
domain that we're
walking into.
About 500 years
before Jesus' time,
the prophet Ezekiel
had a vision
of the glory
of Yahweh
leaving the temple
due to its corruption
before the destruction
of Solomon's temple
by the Babylonians
by decree of judgment
by God
and Ezekiel came.
However,
Ezekiel also prophesied
that one day
God would return
to the temple
and precisely
from the same direction
he had left.
That's Ezekiel 43.
Hopefully we can
untouch that at Easter.
May Ryan get some
cool conversation
out of that.
If you don't know,
now you do.
Israel had two temples,
right?
Solomon's
hands.
So the presence
of God
abhorred
in this first temple.
Solomon's temple.
This is the original.
The blessed by God,
designed by God,
built by King Solomon.
Destroyed by the Babylonians
in 586 BC.
If you guys are like
not history nerds
like this code,
you guys are crazy
and I love it.
This is what I get
excited about.
Because the Israelites
could not keep
the covenant of God,
God has the Babylonians
to destroy the temple.
The second temple
was reconstructed
during the kingdom
of Cyrus I.
But it would go on
to take the name
of Harry's temple
because the Roman
money that was poured
into it as a peace offering
to these new Roman citizens
that were the Israelite
through the nation
of Israel.
Harry's temple
in the second temple
would have been the one
Jesus is navigating
in the gospel.
Jonathan,
the glory of God
is never present
in the second temple
apart from Jesus'
financial entry
into Jerusalem,
which is his
Ezekiel 43.
Jesus coming back
into Jerusalem.
Jesus calls himself
to the temple
in John 2,
19 and 22,
destroy this temple
and in three days
I will raise it up.
Verse 22,
he was speaking
about the temple
of his body.
But I want you guys
to get this,
right?
I'll give you a little
conceptual background,
but the temple
of Solomon's
and in Herod
was seen as,
in a very literal sense,
the house of God,
right?
This abode of God,
this meeting place
of heaven and earth
where the two spheres
combine.
Yeah.
But what is the temple
without the presence
of God?
It's abode, right?
It's brick and mortar.
The holiness of God,
the fear of God
comes from the presence
of God dwelling in it.
That's why I think
Jesus adds
that little part.
Without me,
you can do nothing.
Without the presence
of God,
the people,
the temple
became the identity
for the religious
power dynamic
of Israel.
They became an idol
that they worshipped
instead of the one
from God.
That calls back
to our last idea
that we talked about.
Jesus calling himself
the king diamond,
not Israel.
Jesus is saying
the presence of God
has returned
to Jerusalem.
Jesus is saying
that no longer
will the presence
of God be housed
in this brick
and mortar building.
Jesus is saying
the presence of God
will live in you.
Right?
In this verse.
That's why Jesus says
remain in me
and I in you
apart from me
and you can do nothing.
You are the temple
of the living God.
I hope you feel that way.
Like,
the temple,
Solomon's temple,
and maybe even his,
was the,
one of the seven wonders
of the ancient world.
This is something
everyone knew about
in the ancient Near East.
You are now
the temple
of the living God.
The apostle Paul
drives this point home
in 1 Corinthians.
We'll look at verse 3,
16.
Don't yourselves
know that you are
God's temple
and that the spirit
of God lives in you.
1 Corinthians 6,
19, 20.
Don't you know
that your body
is a temple
of the Holy Spirit
who is in you
cleaning you off
from God?
You are not
your own.
You were bought
with a price
to glorify God
with your what?
Body.
So there's fruit.
We're getting back
to this idea of fruit.
What is it?
And I think you can use
Paul's letter
to the Galatians
as a breakdown
of that.
I'm cool with using that
as an expounding.
But Paul's writings
were characteristics
of the fruit.
that if Jesus' audience
read the disciples
on this way
to the garden,
they would have
understood this parable
to mean the outpourings
of blessings
from the presence
of God.
We need God
to abide in us
so that we can
abide in Him
because we can do
nothing without Him.
Verse 8,
The fruit is a testimony
of God's glory
and we are the branches
of that vine
but the whole point
of that is to bring
God the glory
He so rightly deserves.
The official temple
was where Israel
experienced God,
right?
The place
where heaven
be faced.
Now,
we're the temple
through whom
the whole world
experienced God.
We're to be the place
that all God's
nations
were heaven
be faced.
Because Jesus
abides in us
and we abide
in Him.
And that's why
our role
as temples
of the living God
is to let
this world
see and taste
that the Lord
is good.
Last but certainly
not least,
this idea
of the gardener
is the last
of our three ideas.
But before we unpack
this last idea,
we've covered
Jesus' role
of the true vine.
We've covered
our role
as the branches.
And before we unpack
the gardener's role,
I want to read
Isaiah 5.
I'm going to start
in verse 1
because I think
it gives more
context to what
Jesus is talking about,
especially the
Father's role
as His gardener,
as His father
who cares deeply
for His cross.
Isaiah 5,
verse 1,
and we'll read
through 7.
I will sing
about the one
I love,
a song about
my loved one's vineyard.
The one I love
at a vineyard
on a very fertile hill.
He broke up
the soil,
cleared it of stones,
and planted it
with the finest
bones.
He built a tower
in the middle of it
and even dug out
a winecrest thing.
He expected it
to yield good grapes,
but it yielded
worthless grapes.
For now,
residents of Jerusalem
and Mama Jeter,
please judge
between me
and my vineyard.
What more
could I have done
for my vineyard
than I did?
What more
could I have done
for my vineyard
than I did?
Why would I
expect it
to yield
a good grapes
worthless grapes?
Now,
I will tell you
what I'm about
to do to my vineyard.
I will remove
its head
and it will
be consumed.
I will tear down
its walls
and it will
be tranquil.
I'll make it
a way for you.
It will not
be pruned
or weeded.
Thorns
and briars
will grow up.
I will also
give the orders
to the crowds
so the rains
could not fall on it.
For the vineyard
of the Lord
of the armies
is the house
of Israel.
The man
of Judah
the plant
delighted him.
He expected
justice.
This is God.
He expected
justice
but saw
injustice.
He expected
righteousness
but heard
only
cries
of despair.
I've worked
far into my youth
but something
I've never done
is work a vineyard.
Are we any vineyard
workers?
I mean,
it feels like
a cool application
if you got it.
That's why we have
here a little bit.
I'm seeing
if I have any
vineyard experts
in the room.
I found this
really cool article
which is familiar
with news vineyards.
In Woodstock,
Rachel,
she drinks wine.
The sisters.
So news vineyards
in Woodstock,
I'm sorry,
Rachel,
thank you.
News vineyards
in Woodstock,
Virginia,
which is coincidentally
in its system
of 200-acre
Mennonite farm,
has a really good
article that I
thought would be
instructive to you
as we unpack
John 15.
Winter is the time
dormant vines
are cleaned.
The water cleaned
it off.
An abandoned
Virginia vineyard
was instructed.
Two years
after its last
spring,
the Bible
will have
seats 12 to
15 feet long
and that would
have grown
into the top
of the cross
and collapsed
to the vineyard
floor.
Within another
year,
the vineyard
superstructures,
the posts,
the wires,
et cetera,
will be hidden
under a mass
of foliage.
A year or two
after that,
the roads
will no longer
be recognizable.
Instead of a vineyard,
there will be
an impensable
thicket of tangled
down the seats
and savage competition
for the water
and sunlight
necessary for
photosynthesis.
Because it is
the latter process
by which vines
accumulate
carbohydrate reserves
to survive winter,
vine death
will soon start
among the losers
of what has become
a Darwinian struggle
for existence.
Meanwhile,
what has happened
to the freeze?
Vines that are now
the size of large
hedges will produce
many clusters of grapes,
but they'll be hidden
under a thick
matting of leaves
and will therefore
never ripen.
A few bunches
will get to the top
of the vines
where drastic
birds of the sunlight
will produce
enough ripeness
that the birds
and the occasional
black bear will feed
upon and later
streak the seeds
to ensure
that some of the vines
were written to do
in more ingenial
circumstances.
This is not
how a farmer
does his vines,
right?
It's wild.
So,
next slide,
please.
Pruning aims
as one principal result.
A stand-alone
vine,
total birth-producing
grapes
that are ripe
enough to produce
palatable wine,
right?
That's what we want.
That's what the gardener
divines us to want.
Pruning has a purpose.
Pruning is not
meant to be destructive
or harmful
to the bansons.
It's meant to encourage
healthy growth
and sustainable
harvest.
The Father's role
as vines
just in John 15
is not one of a butcher.
How many times
do you get that image
in our house?
That God,
the vine dresser
is,
according to the
thing,
he scrubbed
so much
this one
time and this
thing.
He's not a butcher.
He's not a madman
hassling off branches
as he feels like
to throw them
into the bone column.
He's an artist.
He's a conservationist.
He's a farmer
who cares very deeply
about his crop
and the food he yields.
He turning to the
unclaimed eye
might be scary.
Piles of branches
among the rays
of the gravestone.
Piles of someone
who has planted
the seeds,
who has built
the place
in the trellis,
who is strung
the wild,
who cares,
who cares very
for the harvest
and especially
isn't acting
carelessly
at the thing
he's worked
so hard for.
He's building
enough.
He's making
sure that the
branches get
what they need
to produce
good fruit.
Piles of the
gravestone
so that when it
comes to one
for the harvest,
all this hard
work is paid off.
And he can
celebrate that
his hard work
had not been
in vain,
but he was
all carefully
planned from
the beginning
of the process.
The fruit
produced by
the branches
that are
connected to
the vine
and for the
glory of God
in his harvest.
The Israel
failed as the
vile of Yahweh
as we read
now their
style of justice.
Our plans,
the church's
plans would
fail apart
from the
true vile of
Jesus.
Without me,
you can do
nothing.
That is
beautiful.
He would
raise up a
vine that
would not
be wild
and unruly
like we
are,
like
Israel is.
He would
raise up a
vine that
would be
faithful.
Jesus,
this image
of the
invisible
God.
See,
this is the
cool part.
This is the
essence of the
doctrine of
eternity,
that no one
other than
God was
capable of
redeeming his
creation
other than
God.
Right?
I could not
pay for your
sins.
I'm not
worthy.
I don't
think anybody
in this
room is
worthy.
But God
and Jesus
raised up
his true
vile.
Our
job is to
be connected
to the
true vile of
Jesus,
receiving
life-giving
sustenance
from the
Spirit to
produce
lasting fruit
for the
Father.
Our
privilege is,
as the
church,
is to have
our identity,
we know we
talked a lot
about identity,
only deeply
and intimately
rooted in
Jesus,
becoming
witnesses that
are honoring
to the
Father as
he lovingly
clips away
everything that's
holding us
past and
producing fruit
that he
desires to
fully usher
in his
creation.
We have
this privilege,
we talk about
this all the
time,
this privilege
of participation
with the
God of the
universe in
his plan for
ultimate
reconciliation
and redemption.
We're not
going to
end with
baptisms,
eventually
assemble,
that's
going to
be
revealed
by
Jesus
about
them.
Today we're
not going to
end with
communion,
we're actually
going to
end with
baptisms,
which I
consider
unfree,
glorifying
to the
Father.
This week,
if you
consider the
claims of
Jesus as
this I
am the
free-binding
statement,
your role
is a
branch,
the
Father's
role as
gardeners,
consider
communion,
the
promise of
heart,
fasting,
silence with
the God
of the
universe.
Remember,
having a
faith in
which the
primary mode
by which we
relate to
God is
doing
for him
does not
mean that
we even
have to
commune
with him.
Our
job is
to be
free,
but we
can do
nothing
apart from
the true
body.
Let's
pray.
Dear
Father,
we thank
you for
carrying
this